Summary

NLP/ML researcher and engineer with over 6 years of experience, ranging from information retrieval and large language models (LLMs) to parsing and distributional semantics. Demonstrated abilities in publishing award-winning papers in top conferences as well as developing NLP systems.

EDUCATION

### Ph.D. (Research Area: NLP, Computational Semantics)

Aug 2019-Jan 2024

The Chinese University of Hong Kong (CUHK)

Thesis: Learning Semantics from Meaning Representations: From Distributional and Graph-Grammatical Perspectives

• Area Chair Award: Awarded to 21 out of 1742 papers accepted to ACL 2024

2024

2015

#### B.Sc. (Hons) with First Class Honors in Computer Science

Sept 2015-July 2019

The Chinese University of Hong Kong

- Dean's List: Awarded for academic excellence in the Faculty of Engineering
- 2016, 2017, 2018, 2019
- Master's List: Awarded to the top student of each major of each class in Wu Yee Sun College 2017, 2018, 2019
- ELITE Stream Student Scholarship: Awarded to recognize excellence in advanced-level courses 2017, 2019
- Computer Science Scholarship: Awarded to top students admitted to the computer science program 2016
- Admission Scholarship: Awarded to high achievers newly admitted to the engineering program

WORK Experience

# Senior Algorithm Engineer (NLP/LLM Team)

Mar 2024-Present

TCL Corporate Research (Hong Kong) Co., Limited

- Design, develop and deploy chatbots based on retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) using open-source LLMs that work on domain-specific bilingual (Chinese and English) data
- Devise a hybrid retrieval strategy and implemented the data pipeline which combines vectorial and keyword-based queries using MySQL, Milvus, and Elasticsearch, thereby replacing team's previously developed method
- Tailor summarization algorithms for clients for more structured and explainable outputs than pure-LLM approaches
- Apply large vision-language models for parsing PDF documents to structured data

#### Junior Research Assistant

July 2019

Department of Systems Engineering and Engineering Management, CUHK

• Researched and developed a transition-based parser for meaning representation graphs

#### Software Engineer Intern

June 2018-Aug 2018

Set Sail Software

• Developed the backends of chatbots and performance analyses tools using Node.js and Firebase Cloud Functions

Selected NLP/ML PROJECTS

## Word Representation Learning (\*SEM 2023; ACL 2024 (Area Chair Award))

- Developed a VAE from scratch for word representation learning using PyTorch with distributed data parallelism
- Outperformed >20 models on the tasks of semantic composition and verb disambiguation, including BERT which uses  $12\times$  more data and  $2\times$  more parameters
- · Hypothesized and confirmed lexical entailment can be learnt by our models from restricted classes of corpora

### Dialogue System with Unstructured Knowledge Access (DSTC9 @ AAAI 2021)

2021

- Led a team that worked on ranked retrieval from an FAQ knowledge base, where we supervised—fine-tuned a BERT model as a reranker using Huggingface and PyTorch
- Participated in the Ninth Dialog System Technology Challenge (DSTC9) and our team ranked 12 out of 24<sup>[2]</sup>

### Text Generation via Semantic Graph Parsing (ACL 2022)

2019-2021

- Developed a probabilistic graph parser from scratch that reconstructs syntactic derivations from semantic graphs, with devised adaptations that improve accuracy, efficiency, and coverage of graph parsing
- Achieved better graph-to-text translation than a neural sequence-to-sequence method under out-of-domain settings

INVITED Talks

Functional Distributional Semantics (FDS) at Scale and Probing for Hypernymy in FDS, 19th DELPH-IN Summit, Language and Information Society of University of A Coruña

Semantic Composition with PSHRG for Derivation Tree Reconstruction from Graph-Based Meaning Representations, Seminar at Foundations of Language Processing of Umeå University, Virtual 16 Sept 2022

Core Skills

Natural Languages Cantonese (native), English (proficient), Mandarin (proficient)

Programming Languages Python, C, SQL

ML/DS Libraries PyTorch, Tensorflow, scikit-learn, Pandas, Numpy, Elasticsearch, Milvus

NLP Libraries PyDelphin, Hugging Face, NLTK, Spacy, Gensim, WordNet,

Others Git, Docker, Google Cloud

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- [3] Chun Hei Lo, Wai Lam, Hong Cheng, and Guy Emerson. 2024. Distributional Inclusion Hypothesis and Quantifications: Probing for Hypernymy in Functional Distributional Semantics. In *Proceedings of the 62nd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers)*, pages 14625–14637, Bangkok, Thailand. (Oral and Poster; Area Chair Award)
- [2] Chun Hei Lo, Hong Cheng, Wai Lam, and Guy Emerson. 2023. Functional Distributional Semantics at Scale. In Proceedings of the 12th Joint Conference on Lexical and Computational Semantics (\*SEM 2023), pages 423–436, Toronto, Canada. (Oral and Poster)
- [1] Chun Hei Lo, Wai Lam, and Hong Cheng. 2022. Semantic Composition with PSHRG for Derivation Tree Reconstruction from Graph-Based Meaning Representations. In *Proceedings of the 60th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers)*, pages 5425–5439, Dublin, Ireland. (Oral and Poster)